[Music]
n
ah
[Music]
hello good evening good day everybody
and welcome to a new episode of the ask
AB show I hope you're all doing very
well and let us see who all is there on
the live chat with us today is the live
chat episode everything all the
questions I'll take from the live chat
so let's see I can see Tanish minalin
Guru Kumar prajwal
sarves Guru Prasad gorov Mr YouTuber kov
amoga pritam as Menor hello
sidhant arrow4 Ajay Kumar akula harpal
MC Lovin
yesz RIT Agarwal akhat Raj rupak vadi
mono Jubal VI Singh garosi akhat
rupak param prit y z ajaykumar snal sain
Vin Ray Ana s shat Prashant T Harel
Sharma VI b z lnl
x27 vishes paraa editz Atul Shan malakar
Amit mikar yeses red ratan priad Dari
disha RK Ka Karan
prajal ar14 prian Anway akill Harley
Davidson
sabana Meep vikrant nikil Raju Anand MRI
Jubal
uh Aditi Banu prakash yeses tarun Mano
Singh zubon Isen pritam Sharma and lots
and lots and lots of other people
welcome all and thank you so much for
being on the live chat so uh in this
episode I will take questions only from
the live chat so let's go ask your
questions and I shall take as many of
these as I can and I'm going to do three
live streams this week it's kind of uh
kind of like in the old days when I used
to do multip mple live streams every
week so I'm going to do three live
streams this week and maybe we shall
continue that in the coming weeks so
please go ahead and ask your questions
let us see
okay VI B says this might be the hardest
question in your life is it Cristiano
Ronaldo or lonel Messi no diplomatic
answers please who's the best I think
it's lonel Messi both are tremendous
players of course and both have achieved
a lot but Cristiano Ronaldo has not won
the World Cup and Leonel Messi has so
overall I think I would go with lonel
Messi I know it's a very controversial
thing half the people will not agree
with me that's all right everybody has
their opinion yeah that's uh what I
think about
it McLovin says My Views about the
interview and the ad campaign of the US
ambassador to India ah yes Mr Eric
garetti he's been in India for a year I
believe and he put out a extremely well
produced video which I have not watched
I watched first three or five seconds of
the of the video and I just clicked away
I guess so I haven't seen it I've heard
it's an extremely well- produced video
better than what any so-called YouTuber
could produce better than what what most
ad agencies would produce but I haven't
seen it and I haven't seen his interview
so no idea I do not consider Mr garetti
to be a person that's very important or
consequential he uh the US needs to have
an ambassador in India so they have one
he is a political appointe he's not a
career Diplomat he's not somebody who
has made a career in diplomacy so uh
he's not really that important the real
uh when it comes to the India us
relationship it is run from the Pentagon
and from the White House to some
extent and from the US perspective and
from India it's Dr J Shankar who is
implementing the Modi policy and so on
so Mr garetti is just a figurehead he
does doesn't really matter of course his
pronouncements need to be taken
seriously because they represent the
official position of the US and so on
but I haven't really bothered to see it
I don't think it's that important I have
not been interested in that so uh that's
all I can say about
that
okay let us see okay Harel says when
comparing France and Prussia who was the
strongest European power would 1871
Prussia beat Napoleon
I think it's hard for anyone to beat
Napoleon when Napoleon was at his his
Peak at the peak of his powers Napoleon
was a force of nature he was
irresistible and it took the combined
might of the British and their Allied
Forces to eventually take him down after
studying him for a long time and he
actually lost because he tried too much
too soon he tried to grab too much in
too little time and also because he did
not not have the advantage of the power
projection and the uh Supply chains and
all that that the British had globally
not globally at that time but yes they
had an extensive network of Supply
chains and all that and they had
tremendous power projection abilities
the British the French did not have that
so Napoleon if he had taken the time to
build that then he would have been
invincible so Napoleon at his Peak when
he was well all over the place and
defeating everyone he was essentially
Invincible for some time at least so
1871 Prussia could they beat Napoleon at
the PE peak of his powers I think that
would be a little difficult especially
if Napoleon had the technological
advances that existed in
1871 1871 is essentially when the nation
of Germany was born the Iron Chancellor
bismar was the founder of Germany
essentially even though he was never the
ruler he was you could say the founder
and the the force behind the UniFi the
unification of Germany so I think think
that Napoleon at his Peak it was almost
impossible for anyone to defeat him
especially if he had the same
technological uh you know advancements
access to that as as the opposing power
so I think it would be it would be have
been hard for Russia or or Germany of
1871 to to defeat
Napoleon of 70 or so 65 or so years
ago okay param bat nagar says what's the
best approach to prepare for succeeding
in Indian competitive exams like neat J
Etc okay competitive exams I'm not a big
fan of that but let me tell you what it
takes to succeed in in any competitive
exam first of all you need to know your
subject really really well the basics
the fundamentals the advanced stuff all
of that you need to have a very strong
very strong grasp on that then that's
not enough it's not enough to know stuff
yeah you may know the you may know
everything there is to know and yet you
may not do well in the exam so how do
you crack the exam like this say you
take the past I don't know 300 years
papers uh the last five years 10 years
exam papers you get those and you solve
them again and again and over and over
again that's how you do it and if there
are in the J I don't think do they have
interviews and all that I'm not sure
okay I'm I've not looked into that for a
long time but in case there are exams
which require you to give presentations
or sit before a firing squad which is
the interview committee and all that you
need to do mock interviews and prepare
all the red on so you need to place
yourself repeatedly in the environment
and in the mil of the exam I mean uh
think about the Armed Forces how do they
prepare for war they do war games they
practice they they do it all the time
they they behave as if they're in a war
situation and that's how they they do do
their drills and their practice and
their whatever it is that they do so you
got to do it that way so you need to
know know the subject very well which
means you need to read all the books
that you may have I mean these are not
exam practice books but whatever you
need to read all the books you need to
know the subject very well and then you
need to do these mock exams take the
last 10 years question papers or last 20
years or whatever is available and solve
them over and over again within that
time frame whatever the time frame is 3
hours 2 hours 7 hours whatever it is and
do that over and over again that way you
will have absolutely no fear of the exam
you'll know exactly how it goes and then
as long as you know your subject really
well why would you not do tremendously
well so that's how you do
it
okay vishes Shukla says why are no
censuses being conducted you mean in
India maybe in India I expect in India
the last census was in 2011 so the
census in India is conducted every
decade every 10 years and we know what
the situation was like in
2021 yes we the the the Corona virus
pandemic so it was impossible to do
anything the the entire
planet was essentially under
lockdown and uh yeah it was it could not
be done so I guess the next uh census
will be done in
2031 unless there are plans of doing it
at some other point in time uh it's
always good to have a sensus and have an
ex a good understanding of what your
population is like what the demographics
are like and so on and so forth
but you know this was like like they say
an act of God there's nothing nothing
you could do about it the country had to
be locked down now we know that the
virus wasn't that dangerous and all but
at that time you never knew you did not
know what the virus was like and what it
could do to your country and it was
imperative to to save as as many lives
as possible so the so that's why it did
not happen Okay you cannot blame the
government for that for not conducting
the census in a in a situation when
where there was a global crisis nothing
you could do about it okay
par bsar says what's going on in
Pakistan occupied Kashmir are the news
media 100% true and what they are saying
well I don't watch the news so I don't
know what they are showing but I am
aware of unrest and protests that are
happening in various parts of Pakistan
occupied Kashmir so the locals in
Pakistan occupied Kashmir are fed up
with the Pakistani oppression with the
oppression of the Pakistan Army and uh
the the
misgovernance the lack of
uh tolerable living standards the lack
of progress the lack of development and
they can see what's happening across the
border in free Kashmir in India's Jammu
and Kashmir they know they can see how
much progress and development there is
tourism is booming people are doing well
the Pakistani terrorism has essentially
been squashed there are some sporadic
incidents here and there which they will
keep doing but overall it's it's Tri
tremendous progress in free
Kashmir and they can see the Stark
difference so they are they are
frustrated they are fed up they want a
better life and that's why there are
protests there is unrest there are
there's violence there's
demonstrations police Personnel are
being beaten up I'm not sure if the
armed forces are being be are being
targeted probably not because the Armed
Forces will respond with tremendous
violence the Pakistan is that's how they
operate but that's the deal so there's
tremendous
misgovernance in Po and Pakistan
occupied Gil balistan there's no there
very poor education system there's no
delivery of services very poor health
care facilities very poor infrastructure
roads whatever you name it it's terrible
in P so the people naturally are
frustrated but that doesn't mean that
they necessarily have any great love for
India please understand that okay uh
these are the same people who conducted
those massacres in in meur and gilg
pistan and all that in in 4748 okay I
don't think they have changed too much
but overall they are frustrated and the
I'm I'm not sure what they what they
want do they do they think that this
violence will give them better living
standards and better delivery of
services and governance I'm not sure or
do they seek independence from Pakistan
do they seek to rejoin the motherland
India I'm not
sure but overall it's it's uh it doesn't
concern us okay uh as as Prime Minister
Modi recently said we have simply shut
the door on Pakistan let them deal with
their problems on their own we're going
to go ahead and develop our country and
that's it so yeah that seems to with the
situation
overall
okay pram Sharma says let us see what
pram has to say I quote the Dal Lama we
are not seeking independent from China
we want to be part of China what's my
reaction and what should be India's Way
Forward as we do give the people of
Tibet safe Heavens in India look the LI
Lama I I think this is what he said that
we seek more autonomy extra autonomy or
whatever within China I think it's a
kind of a practical pragmatic statement
he's kind of resigned to the fact that
he's in no position to change the status
quo in the China is firmly in control of
Tibet uh so I think all he seeks is that
the Tibetans get a little bit better
better deal somewhat better treatment in
in Chinese occupied Tibet because right
now what's happening is cultural
genocide that Tibetan language is being
erased Tibetan kids are being forced to
study in Chinese they are prohibited
from from speaking the Tibetan language
the education system is entirely in
Chinese and uh there is tremendous
repression and oppression they're not
allowed to uh have photographs of the
Dal Lama or to pray to the Dal Lama I'm
not sure if they're even allowed to run
monasteries if monasteries exist they
are tightly controlled and so on so it's
tremendous repression there is cultural
genocide and more than 50% of the
population of Chinese occupied Tibet is
now hand Chinese the Tibetans have
become a minority in their own
land so the Dal probably seeks some kind
of compromise he knows that he is in no
position to change things and that's why
probably he made the statement so what
is my reaction well okay Lama his
Holiness Dal Lama is a spiritual leader
to some extent you could say he is some
kind of political leader but well at
this point in time uh his his Holiness
thead does not really
matter from the political and
geopolitical
perspective okay because he is in no
position to affect any real change in
the world he's a spiritual leader and he
is 80 plus I hope he has a very long
life but eventually he will have to
decide about his reincarnation as well
because that's how the the the
institution of the dalama continues when
one the Lama passes on gives up the body
dies he is essentially
reincarnated in in the body of a new
child and there are you know uh the
llamas and all they look for certain
signs and all that which will identify
some new child somewhere as The
Reincarnation of the Dal Lama so the Dal
Lama needs to announce I mean he needs
to make his intentions clear whether he
does intend to be reincarnated or not if
he doesn't want to be if he in does not
intend to reincarnate then it means that
the institution of the dalama is over
after once he passes on or he could
announce that he will reincarnate
whether in Tibet or outside of Tibet or
within India so he needs to at some
point in time make that announcement
because well he's uh pretty elderly now
more than 80 years old as far as far as
I know and yeah so that is the situation
with the Dal as far as I'm concerned it
doesn't matter what he says because
words have words are
immaterial China is in occupation of
Tibet very firmly in occupation of Tibet
and that is the root cause of the India
China you know issue the Chinese
aggression which began with their
capture of Tibet which which Mr neeru
allowed them to do and actually
facilitated them to do because he
supplied the Chinese soldiers who were
starving with Indian
rice so India uh I think there is no big
influx anymore of Tibetan refugees into
India the Chinese have sealed the
borders essentially Tibetans are no
longer pouring across the border like
they used to do in the 90s in the 1990s
maybe early 2000s it's it has more or
less stopped if anybody does come in
it's a very small trickle if at all so
those Tibetans who have been fortunate
enough to cross over into India they
have reasonably good lives compared to
their uh brethren in Tibet and that's
what it is So eventually whenever the
India China issue will be resolved it
the root cause is Tibet the Chinese the
illegal ilegitimate brutal Chinese
occupation of Tibet once that ends
whenever it does maybe next 20 years
maybe next 100 years I don't know when
let's see whereever whenever it happens
well that is going to the solution that
is the only solution that you can have
to the India China border issue because
they India and China have never had a
border so the Dal Lama his Holiness uh
it's okay what he says doesn't really
matter
overall okay tan my says do you believe
we had Divine weapons during the
Mahabharat period
look do we have evidence of that see
this is how it this is how it goes see
Indian history is tremendously ancient
when you when you talk about Maharana
pratab who lived just a few centuries
ago maybe when was that five four or
five centuries ago right Maharana pratab
people describe him as being seven and a
half feet tall and his armor was 300
kilos and he had a 12T long sword right
do such human beings
exist now now I expect some people will
will get upset because I'm questioning
that look I'm sure he was a tall and
strong and tremendously Brave and
valorous man but I do not believe he was
7 and a half ft tall I do not believe
that his armor was 300 kilos I don't
believe that his sword was 12 feet
long but today because of his
achievements and his tremendous Deeds
people think of him they picture him in
that manner that's just a few centuries
ago that's like for in from the
perspective of Indian history it's day
before yesterday so when it comes
to Heroes of India historical figures
from several thousand years ago just
imagine
how how much their their physical
attributes and their capabilities and
their weapons would be magnified in the
Mind's Eye right so you always embellish
your story generation after generation
and eventually somebody who was very
valorous very brave very capable who did
tremendous achievements on the B field
and all they are given Divine
attributes and we of course India in
India in Hinduism in Buddhism and all
the Indian uh dharmic paths we believe
that we have some Divinity within each
of us and some of us have more of it
some of those who are lucky so SRI
Krishna for example the kind of things
he did did Only a God could do that so
we regard him as an incarnation of
Vishnu the same goes for Sri RAM and so
on and then their weapons obviously
become Divine weapons
but it doesn't prevent them from being
historical figures right so I am sure
these wars these battles happened using
you regular weapons okay that's how I
see it forgive me if if if you do not
agree with me that's how I see it maybe
if there were Heavenly weapons in those
days maybe that was not kug and we are
living in kug that's why there is no
evidence of that left but whatever it
is so I think that they were
tremendously
unusual people tremendously uh
exceptional people and that's why their
weapons and their attributes seem Divine
to
us and maybe they were indeed
incarnations of of the Divine of of uh
Lord vishno and so on but this is how I
see it please do not get upset if my
perspective differs from
yours but do remember that I'm the
first to with the I I have the greatest
amount of respect for our history our
culture civilization the way we look at
it can differ but the respect doesn't
change all right let's take something
else uh
okay uh at the end of the day the the
brain cannot digest facts only stories
this is an incredible way to preserve
our Legacy under this world I do not
doubt the Divinity perfectly perfectly
I I have no disagreement with that uh
this is a great way to to uh preserve
our Legacy and and the history and the
stories and uh feel free to not doubt
their
Divinity I mean the the things they did
were well one could say Divine and maybe
their weapons are also divine
right
okay godov says why is Biden the US
president allowing massive scale
invasion of his country via Texas and on
the northern border uh mainly kistan is
and this pattern is common in Europe
isn't it vote Bank politics okay let's
let's because we're talking about the
the southern border of the US let's talk
let's look at the
map so where is the US and which border
are we referring to okay this is North
America we are talking about the
southern
border the southern border and we're
essentially talking about the state of
Texas the largest state in the United
States Texas it's mainly Texas that is
uh you know facing the brunt of this
Invasion so you have this tremendously
long border that Texas has with
Mexico and it is well I don't remember I
don't have the exact figures with be
right now but over 2 million or so
people have crossed in to the United
States illegal immigrants have crossed
in during the timeline of the Biden
regime
so you can just walk into the
us as long as you don't have a passport
and as long as you are an illegal
immigrant if you want to migrate to the
us legally then you're going to have to
go through a million procedures and
it'll take you 28 years to get a green
card and another 63 years to get the
citizenship but if you come inside
illegally you will immediately get a
nice hot H you'll get nice meals you'll
get a driving license and you'll get to
vote it's a weird weird
country and uh completely undemocratic
and completely illegal the Biden regime
is essentially breaking the laws of the
United States of America can you imagine
that that is this textbook definition of
corruption that is what's happening
there is no question about it that the
Biden regime the Democrats the
Democratic political party is aiding in
are betting massive large scale illegal
immigration on a continuing basis into
the United States okay so why are they
doing that I don't know about the
northern border of the khalistanis and
all that stuff but yeah so why are they
doing that I'll tell you why in the US
you don't need to be a citizen to vote
you just need a driving license a
driving license that's it so once you
come in and you get a job or even if you
don't get a job even if you're welfare
in and uh so what happens is once these
guys cross into Texas or whatever
Southern State they cross into the uh
Biden
regime gives them Transportation either
by bus or by aircraft you know domestic
flights to various parts of the US to
big cities and then they are put into
various locations in these big cities so
if if it's a Somali refugees who are
coming in they'll be placed in a big
city with there are other somalis so
they'll create a Somali Enclave a Somali
ghetto in all somal will soman people
will be staying there so that's V bank
you
see and some of them are put in hotels
some of them can can if if some houses
and apartments are empty which means the
owner is somewhere else they can just
walk into that squat there and according
to the laws of certain States it's okay
to do that it's legal and when the owner
comes back they they can't get their
house back that sort of thing so all
these laws especially in Democratic
states are pro- illegal immigrants and
all and the whole thing is essentially
vote back politics so they are hoping to
win the next election and other local
elections using this tactic it's
horrific and you were seeing this in in
Europe as well I'm not sure what the
laws in various European nations are
like can illegals vote but they can
certainly alter the
demographics so yeah it's it's a
long-term demographic disaster for the
us all these illegals are coming in
there's no way they're going out again
and this is happening on an ongoing
basis ongoing basis every single day so
you have Somalians coming in you have
people from various Southern American
Latin American countries coming in you
have people from the Middle East coming
in Afghans pakistanis Indians Chinese
everyone as long as you throw your
passport you can get in you have your
passport you have to apply through the
usual channels the the regular channels
so the best thing you do is the first
thing you do is you throw your passport
at the border you walk in and then you
say whatever story horrible but yeah
that's a new
world parik say says what is feminism
please
explain what is feminism it's hard to
Define feminism but let you let me give
you a very brief overview of the history
of feminism feminism essentially emerged
in the United States in the well I don't
know 18th or 19th century let's say in
the 19th century look
in the 19th century 18th 19th century
the US is a nation it the US is an
artificial Nation created by settler
colonialism
imperialism land grabbing and
expansionism okay and the majority
population of the US are descendants of
illegal Invaders from Europe who
conquered the land killed off the
natives marginalized those who were left
and took the the land and created a
country that's in brief now these
Europeans who came in and grabbed this
gigantic continent sized land they were
all obviously you know what the religion
was it was mostly Christianity if not
all of them were
Christians so you have this Christians
coming in and Christianity well
historically it wasn't the way it is
today women historically in Christianity
had second class status I mean look at
the history of Europe in the middle e
ages the Medieval ages even very recent
ages when did women get the right to
vote in
Europe I think in a nation like
Switzerland women got the right to vote
in some parts of Switzerland in the 21st
century
only okay so that's the kind of society
and culture you get you you had in
Europe and that's all thanks to
Christianity the pre-christian native
culture of Europe was very different
women had very high status comparative
to that of man men so women were badly
oppressed in North America to make a
long story
short okay they were essentially second
class citizens they had no real rights
they had no right to property they had
no legal equality with men they were
essentially Servants of first of all
their fathers patriarchy Christian
patriarchy and then there were servants
and possessions of the husbands
so it was terrible and eventually there
was the so there was a need to to
emancipate women from this from this uh
depressing and brutal you know life that
they lived so that was the root cause
and and the Genesis of what you call
feminism which was initially a movement
to to to bring equality to seek equality
for women as opposed to men so feminism
I think I I I have to do I have to check
out the names and all I forget the names
of the ladies who were at the Forefront
of the feminist movement in the 19th
century I think they were they also
allied with the black rights movements
and all that in the 19th century and it
it uh it took off essentially as a
powerful movement in the 1950s and
60s and and eventually it got hijacked
by lefties and today it's a whole
different thing today they don't seek
equality they already have equality now
they seek Superior or men so it's it's
totally become warped and the original
intent and purpose has been lost and
misplaced and now it's all about putting
men down in the US and in the West in
the entire Western World and and about
dominating men and about reducing men to
second class citizen status so there's a
lot of mandry in the west
today and that's all thanks to this new
warped form of feminism ISM so yeah
that's feminism but I think it's it's a
it's a topic that merits a more detailed
kind of exposition and maybe I could do
that in the
future
okay okay let's take a look at this
hitan Sharma says five eyes alleg spying
Australia puu and Nar murder links
Canada and the US and vaccine side
effect issues against India I made
elections is aimed at tarnishing Modi or
India the image okay so the Australians
in 2020 or something they reported that
they had uncovered a nest of spies in
their country belonging to a foreign
country at that time they did not
specify which country it was now this
year I think they they they are I don't
know whether it's the Australians or the
US who are saying that it was
India so yeah the Australian government
is kind of saying that it was Indian
spies who were spying in Australia and
trying to infiltrate the Australian
system and so on so forth that's what
they claim do they have evidence do have
they provided evidence no obviously they
have not when it comes to this panu Nar
thing the Canadians and now the
Americans also are are are claiming that
India was behind this and India when it
comes to this panu fellow who is a known
terrorist who is sheltered and harbored
and aided and abetted by the US US
citizen well this panu
fellow uh the US alleges that India
tried to assassinate him not assassinate
kill kill him murder him on us soil and
according to them that's a red line you
cannot cross we can kill anybody
anywhere in the world like sumani like
Ali and whoever else but no other
country can dare do that to one of our
citizens we can kill our citizens that's
fine so it's total hypocrisy but there's
no evidence that India is involved they
have been Pro able to provide no
evidence when it comes to this uh Nar
thing in Canada once again what's the
evidence you make claims where's the
evidence it's like saying L who died in
so and so day where's the evidence no
evidence um then you have vaccine side
effect issues I'm not aware of that I I
this is the first time I'm hearing of
that so I'll not comment about that so
these allegations that India is has a
massive spying operation in Australia
that India tried to kill uh American
Terrorist on American soil or India is
behind the the the murder of some
Canadian gangster Nar all of these
allegations are the object itive is to
first of all pressurize
India pressurize India in the media
pressurize India diplomatically so you
make this allegations then you use them
behind closed doors during diplomatic
negotiations to arm twist to attempt to
arm twist
India um that's the thing and then
obviously you create they trying to
create a narrative that India is U an
increasingly authoritarian Nation it is
behaving like Nation like Nations such
as ch China and whatever uh in Russia
because Russia also is known to
allegedly eliminate traitors on foreign
soil in various ways China also
allegedly perhaps does such things so
they're trying to categorize India in
the same league as Russia and China and
maybe North Korea and other
authoritarian Nations and they also are
painting an image that India's democracy
is backsliding that's something they've
been doing over the past few years so
overall what are they doing is this
aimed
at affecting influencing the results of
India's elections well it won't work
that way and they also know it the more
you accuse India of doing such things
the more Indian voters will be happy
with the government that for the first
time in forever the Indian government is
showing some some guts let's
say right so it's actually going to
increase the votes for Mr Modi so
clearly I think the West knows that the
election this the general elections that
are currently ongoing are a foregone
conclusion Mr Modi will win one hopes I
hope he wins and they also believe that
he will most likely win with a big
margin so then why are they doing this
they are doing this to create a
narrative and set the
stage for attacking
India and maybe do taking some actions
and some steps that are anti-india
during Mr modi's thirdd term so they're
setting the stage for that and when Mr
Modi comes into wins the election and
comes back to Power for his third term
they're going to start with this barrage
of propaganda in the media that the
strong man has won again and they'll
make whatever comments they want to make
and then they'll say that India is
increasingly authoritarian and despotic
and right-wing and what what whatever
terms they fascist and dictatorial and
all that dictatorial yeah and so on so
they setting the stage for
that they're setting the stage they
they're preparing this entire reception
committee to to attack the Modi
government
3.0 after the election results are
announced June onwards so you can expect
the next five years next 10
years to be increasingly Rocky and
difficult when it comes to the India us
relationship and it's going to be the US
that's going to increase L apply more
and more pressure on India in a variety
of ways see the
us from the US perspective India has
limited utility let's go back to the map
and let me tell you what U utility I'm
talking about where's the map where's
the map here's the map see here's the
map I'm centering in the Far East of
India Manipur Burma and all that okay
Burma is not part of India but you get
the point
so this is where you see India and China
from the American perspective India has
limited utility for them the only
utility for them of India is as a
counterweight and counterbalance to
China India is the only nation in Asia
that can stand up to China and it's the
only nation in Asia that China actually
worries about and to some extent fears
okay they will the Chinese will not say
that oh my God we fear India they will
never say
that but they do fear India and you can
that is betrayed by various actions and
comments of
theirs so from the US perspective India
is a counterweight to China and that's
the only utility they have for the for
India that's the only use there for
India but India is growing economically
India's economy is growing and by 20135
if it keeps growing the way it is
growing India is going to be a new
Challenger on the horizon for the US by
once India reaches the 105 trillion Mark
GDP y or more depending on the exchange
rates which will change India is going
to be the new China in the future by
2050 if everything is fine for India
it's going to be the new China and China
will have declined by that time so from
the from the US perspective India is a
long-term competitor adversary threat
whatever they want to call it and
they're going to they're going to make
it increasingly difficult for India to
grow economically
so it's going to be a rocky road ahead
for India it's not going to be a smooth
ride the US is not going to be friendly
with India the only thing the only
utility they
have of for India is as a counterweight
to
China
okay let us see more
questions okay simong sangam says why
has India been silent in the Ukraine
conflict will India be trusted by other
nations if there is another Indo
Pakistan War okay good question this the
Ukraine conflict going on since the 22nd
24th of February
2022 I forget the exact date 22nd or
24th right it's been more than two years
and India has not actually been silent
India has urged both Nations to resolve
their differences through negotiations
through diplomacy Mr Modi has said that
this is not the time for war we should
not have wars and so on so India has
urged both sides to try and resolve the
matter diplomatically through
negotiations go back to the negotiating
table sit across the table face to face
talk to each other and find a solution
try and achieve a ceasefire that's what
India has said beyond that what can
India
do and of course India has its own
interests we are a growing economy a
rapidly growing economy we are still one
of the low income Nations when it when
you look at GDP per capita our GDP per
capita needs to grow our people need to
have better standards of living over the
next 10 years or people need need higher
levels of prosperity over the next 10
years everywhere in every part of India
that will only happen if India's
economic grows at a good pace for that
for economic growth you need fuel you
need energy and the energy source the
number one energy source is petroleum so
need petroleum and Russia is willing to
supply India with tremendous amounts of
petroleum at discounted rat so why will
India not take it we cannot sacrifice
our self-interest for the sake of vague
principles the US is also
importing Russian petroleum and oil and
whatever I'm not the US the West is
doing that much more than India but
that's okay if we do it is bad so the
point is this this is not
an Indian War this is not even an Asian
War this is a European War okay the
Europeans civil say that Russia is a
Eastern nation whatever it's happening
in Europe and it's a proxy war between
Russia and NATO or rather Russia and the
US and the proxy that is being used is
Ukraine so this is not our
problem and I assure you that if
tomorrow there is a war between India
and Pakistan or India and China none of
the Western countries will do do a thing
or or even pretend to come to India's
Aid that is a guarantee take it in
writing from me none of them will come
to India's Aid India knows this India is
anyway on its
own and when it comes to the relations
between India and Russia India and the
West I think the West has always been a
fair weather friend if a friend at all I
mean remember the old days the 20th
century the United States funded and
financed Pakistani terrorism in India
for decades that is the kind of
trustworthiness that they have
demonstrated and even now the proper
Pakistan is a counterweight to China
just as they would like India to serve
as a
counterweight to China and they also
have a counterweight to Pakistan and
Afghanistan so that's the kind of games
these people play you think you can
trust them you cannot trust them
so India has not been silent when it
comes to the Ukraine conflict we have
made it very clear that we are not in
favor of this war happening we would
prefer we would urge and insist that the
Nations find a diplomatic solution but
well that's all we can do what more can
we do it's for them to to find a
solution so I think when it comes to
trust India has nothing has done nothing
that is
untrustworthy okay India has not
betrayed in nation India has not
financed terrorism in other nations
India has not done coups in other
nations it's it's the West that does
that okay so there's no question of
Nations trusting or not trusting India
India the trustworthiness of India is
not under question
anywhere the global South trusts India
India recently brought the African Union
into the G20 for the G20 has existed for
more than 20
years nobody bothered to bring Africa to
the table and give them a seat at the
table India did that India is the nation
that that does this and and helps other
nations in the global South so India is
genuinely trusted even in Afghanistan
even the Taliban trusts India by the way
okay the Taliban doesn't have any ill
will towards
India because India has never interfered
in in Afghanistan or tried to use
Afghanistan as a proxy against Pakistan
India has never done that so when it
comes to the trustworthiness of India
there's no question about it the
question is can you trust the west and
from India's perspective whom can you
trust can you trust the US can you trust
the west or can you trust Russia I think
the answer is pretty clear okay so yeah
there you have
it
okay satam Gupta what are your thoughts
on the announcement of India having six
six aircraft carriers in the upcoming
years this was announced by uh the
defense minister Mr rajnak Singh
today okay map time where's the map
here's the
map
so first of all let's understand a
fundamental rule of thumb let's say
about Naval activities let us say you
have three ships okay three ships let us
say you have three ships okay let me go
to the map so that you get an
illustration of what I'm talking about
uh okay let's say you have three ships
sitting at the Port of vishakapatnam
okay uh in the uh Kalinga mahasagar or
Kalinga Saga Bay of so-called Bay of
Bengal so you have three ships at the
port and you want to deploy these ships
in the Kalinga Saga in the sea of
Kalinga so the question is can you
deploy all three of them at the same
time and the answer is no as a rule of
Thum if you have three ships one will be
actively deployed wherever you want it
to be deployed let's say over here okay
one will be at the Port being refitted
and restocked and and and uh uh
serviced and the third one will either
be going towards the point of deployment
or coming back from the point of
deployment so if you have three ships
only one can be actively deployed at any
given point in time as a thumb rule
so if you have six aircraft
carriers at any given point in time two
can be
deployed it is very hard for all six to
be deployed or even three of them to be
deployed at the same time because they
need to be serviced they need to be
refitted they need to be resupplied they
will need to go from the port to the
place of place of place of deployment or
come back from the place of deployment
to the port and so
on so if you have six you can deploy two
maximum three at the best of times right
now India has two aircraft carriers and
one is operational one is being fitted
with whatever it is so from that
perspective having six is
Good from that perspective but one
aircraft carrier costs about let's say
six five six billion in US dollars so if
you're going to have four more that's
about 2025 billion that you spend now
imagine that you take that money that
$25 billion and you buy submarines with
that let's say one submarine even if it
costs one submarine cost a billion
dollars you will have
25 worldclass
submarines which means at least eight or
nine can be deployed at one any given
point in time now submarines are
invisible they are they lurk deep in the
depths of the ocean very hard to detect
even with the best magnetic anomaly
detector and whatever equipment you have
very hard to detect the true principal
ship of every Navy in the 21st century
is the submarine not the aircraft
carrier aircraft carriers are
impressive what is it that Henri kisher
said in the 20th century he said that an
aircraft carrier is is one is 100,000
tons of diplomacy equivalent right but
not the case today today the the real
danger trip in any navy is the
submarine and India just has I don't
know how many 15 or 16 submarines in
total we need need 50 more at least at
least 20 more
right and aircraft carriers are big
enticing targets I mean they are great
for projecting power and it's it's great
for intimidating weaker countries but in
a hot war between two Nations that are
reasonably well matched aircraft
carriers are great targets and
destroying one aircraft carer is such a
gigantic moral booster for the one who
destroys it it's a disaster
for the nation that loses the aircraft
carrier because it's it's five6 billion
dollars of equipment plus all the
aircraft on top of it all of that
destroyed so I think so there is a
principle in in Naval Warfare which is
called distributed
lethality so India's area of interest is
the is the Sea of sashtra the Sea of
Kalinga and the overall Indian Ocean
region okay it's a gigantic piece of
Maritime real estate and if India if
India wants to dominate this India needs
to have distributed lethality which
means you need to have a large number of
assets distributed over a large area so
wherever a foreign uh ship goes they
should see the an Indian presence but if
you have concentrated lethality in the
form of two or three aircraft carriers
it's hardly visible at all you can
project power through the planes and all
that through the aircraft through the
fighter planes but
patrolling is
ownership and the more assets you have
for patrolling the more of the Indian
Ocean you actually own
right so what you actually should have
is a large number of
smaller cheaper but lethal assets like
destroyers like frigates even missile
boats definitely submarine large number
of different kinds of deadly assets
dispersed and distributed over a large
area that's what you
want that's what makes
sense but okay we're going for six
aircraft carriers I mean it's it's still
just been announced it doesn't mean it's
going to happen next couple of years
maybe it may take 10 15 years to it
maybe 20 years to get the six but in the
meanwhile you need
to ensure that India's distributed
lethality capabilities increase and so
on so overall I think it's not a great
idea I mean if the budget is there
there that you can have 30 more
submarines and whole number of other
assets plus four more aircraft carriers
absolutely go for it but if in the in
the process of getting those four extra
aircraft carriers you're cutting down on
on the number of submarines and
destroyers and other ships you could
have built and that's a
problem that's how I see it I am not a I
mean aircraft carriers are impressive
for sure if you're the captain of an
aircraft carrier my God you're the top
you're the top dog in the Navy right so
everybody would want to have that and if
you are the chief of Naval staff and you
have six aircraft carriers at your
disposal my God what Prestige but
hey the Navy the the military doesn't
exist for someone's Prestige its
purpose is to to deter the enemy and to
serve the national interest and to
project power so the best way to project
power is what we need to go for I mean
if if aircraft carriers do
that cost versus benefit then do it all
by all means but I don't think it's it's
that good of an
idea if if India had a GDP of let's say
right now India's GDP is what $4
trillion if India's GDP was let let's
say 15 trillion by all means have 10
aircraft carriers sure then it's fine
but right now we have limited resources
so we need to allocate those those
resources the best way possible so
that's how I see it I know lots of
people disagree with me military experts
well it's all right that's all right we
can all have our own points of
view Nan ran says is hry Mongolian God
and rudra the same both have TR Trident
no different gods see uh we have in
India Hinduism in Mongolia we have
tingri ISM okay whenever the
English uh gave a name to a religion
which was not Christianity
they put an ism at the end so so
Mongolia is this large country over here
so let's say you are in Manipur okay
Manipur you just go straight North go
straight North straight North straight
North and you will reach
Mongolia so the distance from arunachal
Pradesh to Mongolia is in a straight
line about 18900 km pretty long distance
but not that
long and overall hisor Ally Mongolia was
twice the size it is today half of
Mongolia has been swallowed up illegally
by
China now what is
tengrism so you will have lots of people
telling you claiming that tengrism is a
monotheistic religion monotheistic
religion because it is named after the
god
tangri that is such a bad lie sism is a
polytheistic religion there is the sky
father thingi there is the Earth Mother
umay and there are a whole lot of other
gods and goddesses and spirits and all
that there are elements of ancestor
worship there are elements of nature
worship there is River Worship there is
Mountain worship there is tree worship
there is Spirit Worship and you have the
main Gods like tangri omay and whatever
other gods they have it's a purely
polytheistic
religion
and today you will see lots of Indian
elements in Mongolia so let's let's go
to Google our friend Google and try to
do a search for theism let's do that let
me share my
screen and let's search for TM
TM
angry and if you see the imagery you
will see lots of shamanistic
practices you will see swastikas of
course you will see
swastikas and you will see Trident
Trident let us see
do we have Trident somewhere you will
see Trident in Mongolia for sure
um you have various kinds of
images okay let us search for Mongol Tri
tengrism
Trident so yes you have Shri chingis
Khan with his Trident you have the
Trident in all at the top okay this
is they're say it's Japanese but it's
not it's it looks Mongolian to me and
and so on and obviously people will draw
parallels with Hinduism because we also
have the Trident this is the molum of sh
chingis Khan the great warrior for peace
and you have a trident there and if you
look at the Mongolian symbol the
national symbol of Mongolia
Mongolia
soomo Soo okay Soo this is the soo
symbol or the swu symbol which you will
see all across
Mongolia and it comes from the swam
script which was created by a Mongolian
Buddhist
monk and so on so forth so what what I'm
what I'm trying to say is that there's a
lot of Indian
imagery in Mongolia Indian symbolism
because of the Tibetan connection which
is a whole historical story over
there so these are two separate
polytheistic
Traditions the Indian
Hindu polytheistic tradition Hindu
Buddhist what Jan sik all of that that
is all under one single umbrella which
is the Indian
uh religious paths and you have the
Mongolian tangri tangri tradition which
was separate so uh tangri and rudra or
tangri and Shiva are not the same even
though they have very similar
characteristics from certain
perspectives but they are not quite the
same okay they do both have the Trident
and Mongolia later became a Buddhist
Nation
and not entirely Buddhist I me if you
look at people of Mong today most of
them will say that they're Buddhist but
they will also worship
thingi they will also have elements of
theism in their Buddhist Traditions so
wherever Indian religions
go they intermingle and syncretize with
the local Traditions wherever you go
historically if you go to
Japan okay the Japanese version of what
they call Buddhism has all the Indian
gods and goddesses and it was very
beautifully syncretized with Shinto
which is the indigenous uh culture or or
tradition religious tradition of Japan
and Shinto has more in common with Hindu
Hinduism than with Buddhism by the way
so in in Japan uh Hinduism Buddhism
synchronized beautifully with Shinto in
Mongolia Buddhism synchronized
beautifully with the tangri Traditions
if you go to the Philippines today
Philippines is a Christian country where
the the the Spanish destroyed Hinduism
in the Philippines the Philippines used
to have rajas they used to have Kings
Hindu Kings and the whole nation the
whole population was
essentially Hindu and they practiced
Hinduism but it was once again
syncretized with the indigenous belief
system of the Philippines the same thing
happened all across southeast Asia and
so on right so that's how it
was so yeah that's to make a long story
short tengrism and and Hinduism are
different and tangri and rudra are not
the same even they even though they have
a lot of common and similar
characteristics okay
okay what
[Music]
else okay aniket Singh says who's going
to win the 2024 election what if the
Congress wins please share your
perspective uh I think Mr mod is going
to win which means the BJP is going to
win I I think so and I certainly hope so
I make no no secret of it I am Pro Modi
I'm Pro BJP for the simple reason that
they have done so much to to transform
India over the past 10 years the results
are visible some people disagree some
people think he a dictator some people
claim is a dictator I don't care and if
he is really a dictator then why are the
people who are claiming that he's a
dictator not in jail huh so uh that's a
different matter I think the BJP is
going to win this election I think Mr
Modi is going to win if they do not win
then it's disaster for India that's my
perspective very short very very
straightforward okay theas hello theas
says why didn't the later maratas
destroy the mugul sultanat in Delhi why
make them vasal when they could have
ruled over the whole of India why not
completely abolish them that is a
question to an that's an question to
whose to which I still don't have an
answer I haven't studied marata history
in that much detail especially that part
in which uh the
the the marata Empire expands almost all
over India takes over Northern India
goes all the way to Southern
Afghanistan uh and yet they allow the
the so-called mugul Sultan to rule Delhi
just one little little bit of India why
I'm not really sure
why you're right they should have
abolished them abolished the
sultanate and destroy the sultanate
because they were clearly an
illegitimate foreign occupying
Force so I don't know there must have
been some political calculations behind
this to make them a wasal and so on I
still haven't studied that part in in
sufficient detail to be able to give you
a proper answer but yes it is a question
that is lexed me as well why not simply
wipe it out I mean what legitimacy did
these Turks have in India maybe that
there must be some reason maybe I should
probably study that part of history and
and and see why it was so
okay okay aayushman mat mpati says I
would love to be big and strong maybe 7
feet tall and 120 kilos but very
negative environment here and people say
it's impossible for Indians
well the great Kali is 7 feet tall and
maybe 130 kilos I don't know look 7 feet
tall being 7 feet tall is
extraordinarily rare and unusual
anywhere in the
world even in like you typically the the
nations with the tallest populations I
think the
Netherlands the average height is six
feet I think in the
Netherlands or
61 in Germany the average height of of
males is 6 feet so even in these nations
these nations with small reasonably
small populations somebody being 7t tall
is quite
unusual
so
um and I'll tell you what being 7 feet
tall may look very impressive but it is
extremely uh
problematic you you have you face a lot
of problems and constraints when you are
that tall you don't fit through doors
you don't fit in aircraft seats
you don't fit in your car you don't fit
in in a regular sized bed or a
sofa there are all kinds of problems and
with that height your spine will have
increased stress and all that you may
have medical issues unless you are super
fit and you will take a lot of time to
to you know build up your mus muscle
mass and all that and having a weight of
120 kilos I don't think that's
sustainable over a long period of time
okay so I know it looks impressive and
yeah I'm superior I'm better that's the
feeling you'll get if you're like that
but I don't think it's really
desirable I I'm reasonably tall but I've
never wished that I was 7 feet tall I
never did that uh so but let's say you
want you want to be 7 feet tall so is it
possible I don't know what negative
environment you are experiencing because
I'm not familiar with your circumstances
but uh let's say you want to grow to the
fullest extent of your genetic potential
what well then assuming you are a
teenager let's say you're 15 or let's
say you're 14 and you want to reach your
genetic potential whatever height is
encoded maximum height is encoded in
your jeans well then you should eat a
very clean diet live have a very clean
lifestyle exercise regularly go to the
gym or go to the track and field track
and work out run every day be very
Physically Active eat very good food
drink plenty of fluids and water water
not
fluids not Coke or whatever else and
have your 8 to 10 hours of sleep if you
do all that you will most likely reach
your genetic potential but everybody has
a certain
limit extent to which they can grow in
height so that all depends on your
genetics some people may have it may be
65 for some people it may be possibly 7
feet tall for some people it may be 510
or 5'6 who knows so the genetic cards
that you've been dealt were dealt by the
Gods there's nothing you can do about it
all you can do is do your best to reach
your genetic potential there's no such
thing as it's impossible for
Indians you know in the 20th century I
believe the average height for the
Chinese people was males was 53 54 or
something Chinese were very short today
the average Chinese male is 5'7 I think
58 I'm not sure it's 58 57 the Japanese
males were very short in the 20th
century same thing like the Chinese 53
54 today I think the average height of
Japanese men is 5'8 so it all depends on
your nutrition and lifestyle India has
gone through a couple of centuries two
and a half centuries of British induced
famines okay so the the lifestyle has
been affected by that and your diet has
been affected by that starvation food is
now part of your tradition traditional
food traditional diet you don't realize
that for two centuries you were forced
to eat such things your ancestors and
then because of that because they were
eating this for two and a half centuries
it became your
tradition but before the British
occupation of India your ancestors of
that time would have had a very
different diet which you don't realize
because nobody has taught you that your
history teachers won't tell you this so
you have to eat the right kind of diet
and I think I don't think there's
anything like Indians cannot be tall or
any such thing you you have lots of tall
Indians as well so anyway that is how I
see it Curr n is back hello sir in spite
of having so much talent why has India
not won any Nobel Prize or International
prize in Natural Sciences or in
mathematics uh will you make any course
in
physics okay couple of questions here
okay so when it comes to mathematics you
don't have Nobel prizes you have the
fields medal which is an even tougher
thing because it's given out once in
four years I believe and you have to be
less than 40 years old to get a Fields
medal mul mul bav has won the fields
medal and uh was there any other Indian
I'm not sure I can remember remember
manjul bav who is obviously I think
indian-american or whatever so that that
tells you that tells you a story why has
why have Indians not won a Nobel Prize
in the Natural Sciences in recent times
because of the crappy Indian education
system garbage garbage junk trash the
Indian education system is garbage the
Indian academic system is is mediocre at
best don't get me started on that I mean
show me one Indian
academic in pick any University and show
me one Indian academic who's doing
worldclass work or one academic who is
capable of doing worldclass research the
Indian education system excels at
identifying and destroying talent and
promoting
mediocrity and the Indian academic
system the system of promotions and all
that that also promotes mediocrity and
and and suppresses and marginalized izes
Talent you need to be good at all the
non-academic work you need to be good at
politics and blah blah blah to to Advan
to uh you know high ranking position in
in any physics department or whatever
Department chemistry Department you
know when you go back to the beginning
of the 20th century Neil boher was the
head of Department in in The bohar
Institute before he was 30 years
old all the major advances in quantum
physics and later quantum mechanics were
done by young
men Heisenberg was in his early 20s when
he came up with Matrix mechanics and the
uncertainty
principle
uh who else POI was a young man po did a
tremendous amount of work yes didn't he
Einstein was was in his mid 20s when he
came up with those five brilliant papers
in the year
1905 uh so many others I um I can think
of the only old guy out there was plank
1900 when he derived the
equation and and came up with the
quantum with with
quantization and you had schinger who
was in his 40s when he came up with wave
mechanics the schinger equation my point
is you need to be you need to promote
young talented
people but if you are in your 20s today
you are simply trying to find your place
in the academic system and you have
another 20 years to climb before you can
become a assistant professor or full
Professor or whatever it's it's horrible
it's it's a Daily
Grind and so on so the system is so bad
system is so bad first of all that
there's no chance of any great research
happening in
India I mean if you look at the iits
they have so what sociology departments
and Humanities departments and God knows
what so much of the funding is going to
that
stuff anyway iits are about technology
not about pure Sciences Natural
Sciences but there's hardly anything
happening if there are some good
scientists hidden away somewhere I'm
sure there are but I don't think the
environment is conducive for them to do
any good research proper research
because you know when you are a
scientist researcher in the Natural
Sciences you need to spend a lot of time
thinking you know a physicist may be
staring out of his or her window for for
six hours and you may wonder what the
hell is this person doing we are paying
them to work excuse me they are
working staring out of the window for 6
hours doing nothing is actually working
this thought going on here so that's a
very different world and they need that
space and they need that time but that
you won't find in India the environment
isn't right in India for doing research
that's one and secondly there is bias
against Indians that is also there but
that's a whole different problem so I'll
not blame others I'll say that the
Indian academic system is garbage it is
rotten to the core okay okay corrupt and
political
politicized that's why Indians are super
talented you you transform the education
system and you you you make it
meritocratic and and clean I promise you
the research will just take off in India
in directions you can't even
imagine the the next Golden Age of
physics could come from India if you
have the right environment in the Indian
academic system in the Indian University
system have you gone to a Indian
University it's run by non-academic
staff those clerks and peons and those
people the
administrators and in every Department
the head clerk has more power than the
than the than the head of department and
if you if you meet the head of
Department most of these heads of
Department are like glorified clerks
they don't do any research they don't do
any science they just administer and
that's the glorified position you know I
want to be the head of department so I
have the most power and I can tell
everybody what to do and I have the
funding and budget in my hands and so on
what about your research what about your
work who
cares so yeah that's why sorry for the
long answer but you ask this question
you you'll set me
off
okay now what else aha McLovin says can
you tell us about the Iran Port deal and
the threat of us sanctions yes so once
again let's go to the map where where's
the map where's the map here's the map
where's the map so we're talking about
the Iran Port deal so we I'm sure we are
familiar with the map of India so now
let's go
westwards the Sea of sashtra the Gulf of
Oman the Persian Gulf now there is this
temporary Nation artificial Nation
between India and
Persia which is Pakistan and you go to
the uh makran Coast in baluchistan you
have the port of guad in pakist
okay and if you go westwards further
there is another big Port which is
chabahar in Persia in Iran so this port
has been handed over essentially to
India for the next 10
years that's the deal that India and
Iran have just signed this is the port
that we are talking about these are
satellite images okay chabahar Port this
is the one so India will essentially
operate this port for the next 10 years
and what that does is that it allows
India to bypass Pakistan and access
Central Asia through Iran and not just
Central Asia so it will bolster the uh
North South transport Corridor which
will connect India to Central Asia and
to Russia it will also allow India to
access Afghanistan bypassing Pakistan so
India just has to send hiips to
chabahar in order to send materials and
goods and whatever else into Afghanistan
as well as as as to Central Asia and
even to Russia and to get Consignments
from these places as well so no need to
go through Pakistan to reach Afghanistan
and Central Asia now it will be done
through cha Bahar so that's great for
India that's great for Iran that's also
great for Central Asia all the countries
in the region and the Americans are
unhappy because the Americans don't like
Iran you know what they did recently
right the the entire Israel Iran thing
the tensions are still
high uh Iran Iran's Embassy Iran's
Consulate in Damascus was targeted by
the Israelis Iran hit back Israel hit
back and so on so forth and the
Americans a couple of years ago few
years ago they assassinated the Iranian
General kasum suani in Iraq and all so
long history between the US and
Iran and the Americans have imposed all
kinds of sanctions on Iran just like
they've done on Russia and India doing
this agreement with Iran is something
the Americans are very unhappy about and
they publicly threatened that May
sanction
India now imagine the US sanctioning
India that is not the act of a friendly
nation that is an overly hostile
act imposing sanctions you know the only
Authority the only legitimate Authority
that has the right to impose sanctions
anywhere in the world is the United
Nations when the US does this it's kind
of like an act of War okay the US
recently imposed sanctions on China more
sanctions
uh check out Biden's tweet I'll I'll not
put it up over here because it's a
different matter so that's the thing so
like I said once again let's go back to
the map and like I said before let me
reiterate this India has limited utility
for the US the only utility that the US
sees for in India is as a counterbalance
counterweight to China but they have
propped up Pakistan as a counterweight
to India as well to keep India off
balance at any given point in time if
they need to they can activate Pakistan
the terrorist nation which they aided
and abetted for
decades beyond that utility the
Americans see India as a long-term
adversary and competitor because India's
economy is growing because India has to
grow its economy to have reasonable
living standards in India and to reach
its real potential historically the past
2,000 years most of the past 2,000 years
India was the world's largest economy I
not making this claim it is Angus micin
research that has proven
this so India eventually will regain in
its historical position it's a natural
process and the Americans would not like
this to happen because it will displace
them as
look put yourselves in the shoes of the
United States for a for a moment the US
is is the world's largest economy the
most powerful Nation it has more than
800 military bases outside its territory
all spread all across the world it is
the only superpower tremendous power
projection and any self-respecting
superpower will make sure that no
competitor is allowed to
emerge they already made a big mistake
with China and now they are trying to
rectify that mistake
so the situation is such that if India's
economy keeps growing let's say 6 7 8%
per year for the next 20 years even the
next 10 years then by 2035 India is
going to start showing signs and
symptoms of being the next China okay
especially if you have a good leadership
the kind of leader we have right now so
that's what worries the US and that's
why they're going to make things
difficult for India they're going to do
whatever it takes increasingly over the
next few years to hamper India's growth
and to hurt India's national
interests and they will resort to
bullying tactics arm twisting tactics
they may impose sanctions at some point
in time and so on so we have beginning
see all this and we also already see the
media barrage against India the
vilification of India and characterizing
India as as an authoritarian Nation as
Modi is a dictator and saying that
India's democracy has been backsliding
and minorities are under threat in India
and blah blah blah blah blah hey what
about the US minorities the Native
Americans what happened to them so it's
all hypocrisy but they have earned the
right to be hypocritical by being so
powerful so yeah so the future of India
us relation relations isn't going to be
very
good the next 10 years after that we
don't know okay we can talk about the a
10 year Horizon at best but beyond that
I'll not talk about it there you have
it
okay uh schools are a
disease ask abijit how to ignore toxic
Souls like you're so smooth in ignoring
questions you don't want supposedly
waste your time uh look okay I see when
it comes to taking questions I mean I
have several hundred maybe several maybe
more than a thousand questions over here
on my timeline I obviously cannot take
all of them right so I'm going to have
to quickly scroll through the question
and pick whatever catches my eye out of
all the questions here and a question
that is relevant and hopefully gives you
some kind of value the answer to that
question should give you some kind of
value so I pick questions in real time
you all asking me questions right now I
pick questions real time just with those
one or two criteria in mind that it
should be an interesting question and
the answer should give you some actual
value that's how I do it so I don't
ignore questions I just pick and choose
questions that would Pro hopefully give
you the best value um now how to ignore
toxic
Souls
well that's a good question how do you
ignore toxic
people in some cases you can't
let's say you are a student in a school
in a class and you have let's say the
typical Indian classroom let's say 50 50
students boys and girls let's say half
half now you are stuck in that class for
one year at least let's say you're in
the eth standard you're going to be with
them until the 10th standard so three
years with them what can you do about it
you're gonna be stuck with them so you
can't really ignore them as such but you
can minimize your interactions with any
of those who are toxic you can do that
uh that's one thing if you have if you
are let's say an employee in an office
in a workplace in a company then once
again you're stuck with all those people
your your co-workers and your bosses
sometimes you have toxic bosses
sometimes you have toxic co-workers what
can you do about it you either move to
another department or a different
company or you just put up with it and
you just carry
on and uh don't pay too much heed to
such people sometimes there's nothing
you can do about it sometimes you have
to interact one one and then you have to
find ways of dealing with the
toxicity so every situation is different
all circumstances are unique in some
ways but what you have to
remember is
that you owe them
nothing and you don't need to live up to
their
expectations you don't need to take what
they say seriously when you are in close
proximity with somebody
okay let's say you have a toxic boss so
there's nothing you can do about it and
some bosses are are like that they're
going to just keep on putting you down
and keep on saying that you're not
performing well or you have this problem
or that problem this defect that defect
and you're going to have it daily the
best thing you can do is if you are
stuck there for some time you don't have
any other job offers for at least the
next let's say six months or three
months then you cannot let that affect
you don't start believing what they are
saying and try and find ways of moving
on So eventually uh or you could fight
them fight back not physically but you
could also lash out at them and be
equally
toxic U say it's it's entirely up to you
what what methodology you use for
self-defense or going on the offense my
main thing is that I I prefer not to be
in contact with with toxic people if
there are toxic people in your viit cut
them out in case you can't cut them out
limit the exposure to those people and
so on so we all look I've lived a long
life obviously I've come in contact with
all kinds of toxic people in in during
my education in
school College University I'm sure
teachers Co
classmates in in uh during my
professional career as well of course
you have that see so you got to find
ways to deal with it the main thing you
remember you have to remember is that
don't allow people's criticisms and
whatever affect you personally never
believe that nonsense all right that's
what I'll
say red says what happened to the skians
in Central
Asia why did they disappear from Central
Asia and if they haven't disappeared who
are their modern day descendants in
Central Asia let's go to the map is a
good question yes this is uh so Central
Asia essentially is
uh the step
region from Eastern Ukraine all the way
through thean through the Caucasus
region Northern Caucasus
region and the STS kazakistan usbekistan
turkistan kistan tajikstan and so on and
present day
sang so-called East turkistan the the
western part of the present day nation
of China all of that is Central Asia and
2 and a half thousand years ago that
this entire large region was called
skiya it was inhabited by the Kian
people so we Indians and our Iranian
friends also called them the shakas so
it was called sakan this entire region
shakana skians and they are classified
as an Iranian people they're actually an
Indo Iranian people and 2,000 years ago
roughly they entered India in invaded
India they were fleeing from the kushans
and the kushans were fleeing from the
Huns very funny story okay the skians
entered India from the Northwest they
subjugated over time the indog Greek
kingdoms and they conquered various
parts of India northern and western
India there were the northern chats and
the Western chhatra mahak chatas they
were all skan origin people the northern
Chups were obviously naturally located
and Their Kingdoms were in Northern
India the Western satraps the mahak
shatas Their Kingdoms were in Gujarat
the Gujarat region which included Sy
also in those times they controlled the
great ports of Gujarat which connected
India all the way to uh Mesopotamia and
Egypt and all the way to Greece and uh
Rome so these skians a large number of
them migrated to India conquer invaded
India conquered parts of India ruled
India for some time and settled down in
India and assimilated into into the
Indian population so their descendants
are all over India today all over India
all over Pakistan all over Afghanistan
the descendants of those skians so
that's one answer to your question lots
of Indians have skan some skan ancestry
maybe 5% 10 10% maybe 30% we don't know
they all look the same so the thing is
when the skians came into India and
mixed with the Indian population there
was no cultural or relig I friction why
is that because they were the same
culture the skians were Sun worshippers
they were
polytheists and the language was also
quite quite similar to Indian language
so they were able to assimilate into the
Indian population very harmoniously so
that is the skians and India what about
the remaining
skians well those remaining skians some
of them their descendants still live in
the Caucasus
region uh today the religion is a
in the dagistan and
uh dagistan region and Cha region the
language is called iron I think in this
region uh the Georgians Armenians Aeris
are not skians descendants of skians but
the people of chichia Etc the Caucasus
region many of them are and when it
comes to the kazakistan usbekistan
turkistan kyrgistan all Tajikistan
region well and even the UR Etc these
people are descended
from turkic males and skan females let's
just put it that way okay because of the
tury conquest of this region so
all well most vestiges of schian culture
and language were wiped out everything
was replaced by the turkic language and
turkic Customs the only thing that
remains is 50% or so s
genetics in the
region an entire culture wiped out by
the
Turks
okay what's
next will vi v Ras Swami become VP under
Trump well I don't know what Trump is
thinking and what he will decide the me
there's talk that he will make uh what's
her name p gavard his VP I mean that's a
possibility that is being considered
seriously so I don't know who he will
choose in the end he will have his own
calculations he's very secretive from
that perspective he
doesn't you know let people know what he
is thinking as any good leader would you
know keep things uh you know secretive
so uh it is likely that VI if Trump wins
will get some high ranking position in
the Trump cabinet in some in some form
of or the other it's likely but VP I'm
not sure maybe VP is too much of a leap
for somebody who has no actual political
experience or governance experience so
maybe he will get some good position in
the Trump cabinet something in which you
can really fight the media or whatever
because VI is very combative and really
good at answering questions and and and
uh
arguing logically constructively so
that's what I think I'm not sure if he
will get the VP position the coveted VP
position
okay technical an says should a student
aim for mastering a skill after the 12th
standard or Target top colleges as we
are the youngest country and still
engineering and Doctor trend is
rising uh after the 12th standard I look
it depends on who you are and what your
aims and objectives are
uh if you want to let's say join a
certain
profession then you would need to ma
Master those skills let's say some
people want to become Chartered
Accountants because there's a lot of
money to be made in that I'm not sure
it's a it's a very interesting field but
there's a lot of money to be made I I
hear because everybody needs an
accountant so let's say you want to be a
CA chartered accountant well you will
need to master that those skills well
it's essentially basic arithmetic but
I'm sure there is you know accounting
and I don't know whatever is there in CA
CS skills so you would need to master
that let's say you want to become a
rocket scientist you want to join ISRO
or you want to start your own company
well you would need to learn
aerodynamics and you know rocket rocket
science propulsion and all all those
things right so I think it depends on
what your objective is if you don't have
an objective then you will not know what
to do but if you have a clear vision of
where you want to be by the time you're
25 or by the time you're 30 then you can
plan step by step so when you're doing
your 12th you're typically 17 years old
right 17 18 what is it 17 I think let's
say 18 let's say it's 18 you do your
12th exam when you're
18 and then you have the question of
whether you go to a college and do get a
degree bachelor's degre and then go to
university and get a master's degree or
do MBA blah blah blah all of that will
depend on what you want to achieve so
you need to have a clear Target for
where you want to be in life career-wise
when you're 25 and also when you're 30
you need to have very clear vision of
that and then you break it down
backwards okay see let's say I am at
this position when I'm 30 so what would
I have done to reach there and you then
you work backwards and that's how I do
it so it entire it depends entirely on
what you want to achieve and what
objectives and vision you have for your
life uh in case it is a specific career
then you would need to acquire those
skills you know so for that and yeah
colleges do you go to a top college do
you go to a medium college do you go to
a regular I don't know not a top college
I think if you want to go into the job
market you will need to go to as as top
a college as possible because it looks
great on on a resume and when you have
are just starting out they look at your
academic record track record so if you
are always stood first and you went to
the most brilliant college that you can
imagine then you will get the job in a
top company but if you want to be an
entrepreneur then doesn't matter if you
want to be go into business you want to
start your own business you want to be
an entrepreneur then I would say that
Acquire the skills for entrepreneurship
in business after the 12th forget about
degrees but then you will not get good
jobs so you better be good at business
and so on so it depends entirely on what
you want to achieve so know what you
want to do
okay all right what's what's next what's
next
um Shadow says what to do to get back
our areas from China Pakistan why not
use blockchain in election voting I
think it'll be pretty safe and no one
can doubt as anyone can see the vote
casted
casted okay when it comes to
areas that we need to take back from
China Pakistan Etc look these processes
take time if you look at the maps of the
world and the
Nations decade upon decade over the past
200 300 years you will see maps
constantly changing Maps change all the
time National boundaries change all the
time it depends on which nation has is
more powerful which nation is less
powerful power is like pressure the more
powerful you are the more outward
pressure you exert and that's how Maps
change borders change the more powerful
you are you are the more outward
pressure you exert and the map will go
outwards the lines of the map will go
outwards and you will get more territory
that's how it goes so what should we do
to do that get become more powerful
India has to become more powerful which
means the economy needs to keep growing
for the next 20
years as the economy grows the military
power grows becomes more and more
massive and eventually you will get your
territories back most likely without
having to fire a single shot
so that's what India needs to do uh
blockchain in election voting I
look no matter what you do people will
question people will have questions
people will raise questions doubting the
voting mechanism doubting EVMS if you
don't have EVMS if you cast paper
ballots and see the kind of rigging you
see in the United States do you remember
the 2020 elections that Trump lost do
you have any idea of the of the
election uh
abnormalities malpractices and whatever
else happened lots of votes were counted
twice in some districts some votes were
not counted at all because they were
counting these paper ballots
manually so if you if you do manual
ballots paper ballots there are lots of
problems people can just rig the
election by capturing boots and stamping
entire lots of
ballots if you have electronic voting
then some people will raise other
questions there is no perfect system so
I have not thought about blockchain in
elections and voting maybe it's a good
idea but I haven't really thought about
that or looked into that matter yet but
I think every technology can be hacked
every there is no
perfect uh method
anywhere okay what's
next
[Music]
um H says India has extended $50 million
support to the males despite despite res
infections also recent elections show
that people support Mr pazu Mr
muu showing people poor people to people
relations thoughts about this you know
the Maldives do we know what the
Maldives are my dear friends let's go to
the map where's the map where's the map
here's the map so there is something
called The lakad chagos
Ridge and the maldiv are part of that so
the chos region is here Lex islands are
over here okay and down south you have
the malds so the males are this weird
nation that oscillates vacillates from
pro-india to pro-china Pro India Pro
China Pro India Pro China so you have a
pro India government for a while then
the GL government is overthrown and the
pro-china government comes to power then
that stays in power for a while for a
few years then you have a pro India
government that comes back and then you
have a pro China government again so
right right now we have Mr Pazuzu sorry
Mr muuu who is the leader of the
Maldives he is virulently anti-india and
pro-china and his party got a sweeping
majority in the in the elections that
happened recently which means the people
are okay with it the people agree with
this anti-india sentiment India
out okay now the deal is this the
Maldives are in a strategically
important
location and we don't want China to make
too much Headway there so we are stuck
with the situation we as in India we are
stuck for at least 5 years with an
anti-india dispensation in the Maldives
now what do we do about that if we
completely cut off relations with them
China will get a free March into Mal
into the Maldives they already uh you
know building infrastructure and all
that in the Maldives the
Chinese and uh if we completely cut off
relations then the Chinese will get an
even stronger presence in the Maldives
so we are kind of stuck
between two bad
choices stuck between a brick and a what
a rock in a hard place kind of it's not
a nation that can really harm India but
we don't want a Chinese significant
Chinese presence in our
backyard so we're going to have to
swallow this pain for some
time and uh cooperate to whatever extent
is possible with the MS give them some
money you know what is $50 million from
a geopolitical perspective it's a few
grains of
sugar okay let me just put that in
perspective it's a couple of peanuts
it's not a whole lot of money $50
million so yeah you give that support to
them you keep the relationship going in
in some in some Manner and what you then
do is that you uh ensure that the next
time there's an election and so on the
right kind of government comes to power
and you do that in a in a proper manner
not by not by interfering in their
electoral process like the Americans
would do or doing a coup but you do it
properly in in a nice man so that's what
I would say it's it's a process it's a
long-term process and we're gonna have
to deal with five years of this nonsense
this guy is so annoying Pazuzu
muu why was he keep saying Pazuzu
reminds me of The Exorcist is
movie okay what next
technical an says are you into
spirituality have you ever experienced
Oneness
um spirituality well look I am not an
I'm not an
atheist I do follow my ancestral
Traditions Hindu traditions for
sure so it's it's kind of complicated
spirit I don't know what spirituality is
I do respect our civilizational
traditions
I will visit
temples and and pay my respects to the
gods I do that and I'm very happy to do
that so if that is spirituality I'm into
spirituality I don't know what else
spirituality
means uh some people would say that I am
spiritual but not religious which means
that I will meditate and do some manra
jaing but I will not go and visit a
temple and not pray to any God I don't
know what exactly it means so I'm not
into that sort of pseudo spirituality or
whatever it is
uh I am a Hindu and I'm happy to be a
Hindu proud to be a Hindu and I do pay
my respects to the gods of my ancestors
of our ancestors whenever I can and
that's about
it
okay shiti ji says what are your views
on people calling Modi g a
dictator it's very simple look if you
can call the leader of a country a
dictator and nothing happens to nothing
will happen to you it means that guy is
not a
dictator simple test go to
China go on their social media and call
sh Jinping a dictator say that shenping
is a dictator what's going to happen to
you within half an hour the cops will
arrive and they'll teach you a lesson
you'll never forget first of all you'll
be behind bars for a few years is and
that's not all that will happen to you
that is dictatorship go to North
Korea okay go to North Korea Pyongyang
and stand in the big Square over there
and say that Kim jongon is a dictator
down with king king Jong King Jong-Un
what's going to happen to you you will
never come out of Korea alive North
Korea alive that is a
dictatorship over here anybody can say
whatever they want to Mr Modi and they
know nothing's going to happen to them
but there are certain states in India
where you can't say a word against the
ruling dispensation there okay I
allegedly I'm not naming anybody okay or
any state but that's what you have so is
that dictatorship is Mr Modi a dictator
really so the people who are doing that
serve a certain agenda they have certain
pay masters I imagine I don't
know but I imagine they have they are
being
paid to make such statements and and
creat such
propaganda and well I would say it's
it's deeply unfortunate that some people
will will sell their country at the
altar of foreign
money so I
say
okay Tanish Arya says how do you how to
start the Journey of being a
polymath you got to read a lot and study
a lot
I mean if you think of polymaths you can
think of Leonardo D Vinci he was a
polymath he was a great artist he was
also interested in anatomy he did
dissections ctively at night he was also
into into engineering and Science and
whatnot so that's a polymath so to be a
polymath you need to have expertise in
multiple domains in multiple Fields you
need to be great at let's let's let's
say Arts so you need to be great at
drawing in painting let's say one
example you need to be great at
mathematics you need to be great at
physics you need to be great
at engineering so multiple disciplines
that are not connected to each other and
you you are an authority or an expert in
like three or four of these that's what
you mean by being a polyman that's a
very difficult thing most it's not for
most people I would say I don't know one
out of 100,000 one out of a million
would be a polymath would be capable of
being a polymath so I don't think it's
something you need to Aspire for what
you need to Aspire for is to be an
expert in one domain on one field and be
really good at that so try so start with
that whatever it is that you think you
you are really well suited to to do try
and gain expertise in that then you will
find that that will take time so once
you do that then you may feel
that that was enough you know once you
reach the level of an expert in
that so if you really want to be a
polyat to spend all of your time reading
and studying multiple things in multiple
disciplines and it's going to take you
at least a decade or two to actually
become a polymath so I'm not sure if it
is something you should even try to do
mia if that's what you want it's going
to take you a lot of time and effort but
all the
best okay
um okay what else do we have we I
already spoke about
uh I already covered this some time
ago uh Dr J Shankar when are we going to
see J Shankar G on your podcast well
please ask Dr J Shankar he can always
come
anytime my podcast is open for him let's
see
whenever okay
Dian dber says history of Roar cast in
Arana I I'm I'm really sorry I do not
have much knowledge about about this
matter about the history of the Roar
people Arana I'm I'm sorry this is
something I don't know
about okay Leo says why don't you make H
videos in
Hindi I'm more comfortable with English
mental colonization you see I spent my
whole life my entire education system
was in the English medium and everything
I've studied and read in my life has
been in
English I'm better in English I'm better
at a foreign language than in Hindi
which is actually something that is not
something to be proud of but that's
where I where I am okay so that's why I
don't make videos in Hindi I do appear
on other channels in which I speak in
Hindi and you will see that after some
time English comes out and then I try to
go back to Hindi and then again I'll
lapse into English that's one reason
second secondly the Hindi I have learned
isn't the best
Hindi okay the Hindi that people
typically speak in India is is filled
with foreign loan words Arabic Persian
and Turkish loan
words when you say
Kebab that's a Turkish word when you say
chiger liver that's a Turkish
word Turkish when you said t
t that cooking instrument that's a
Turkish word you may not be even aware
of it I don't like using foreign words
when you say w it's either persan or
probably
Arabic we should use the word Sami so I
fear I'm I'm I'm worried that I'll lapse
into using words that are not Indian in
origin and and I dislike that intensely
so that's why I prefer not to speak in
Hindi because I don't want to pay my
respects to the to the language of our
occupiers foreign occupiers by uttering
words from those
languages I'm still okay with Persian
because they are anyway closely related
to us the Persians our cousins but uh
I'm not fond of the Turk Turkish
language because of what the Turks did
to India and Arabic is in no way
connected to our cultural language I
have nothing against the Arabic people
wonderful people overall today's
Arabs um so yeah so I prefer not to
speak in Hindi for for these various
reasons Hindi is today's Hindi is not a
pure language you know the the
grammar is is based on Sanskrit grammar
why the prits which came
later and and the vocabulary is mostly
Sanskrit vocabulary but lots of foreign
lone words Arabic tan Turkish and
Persian not a big fan of these languages
and I so that's why so for these reason
I prefer not to speak in Hindi unless
I'm invited to some Channel and they
want to speak in Hindi in which I will
make I'll make an effort and hopefully
not speak too much English and hopefully
speak uh should the reasonably should
the Hindi
okay hey hey hey hey hey Anway Sharma Le
Zepplin versus Pink Floyd
one1 no maybe Le Zepplin The problem
with ping Floyd you know ping Floyd is
probably the greatest rock band of all
time
but the problem is that they are
gloomy you listen to them you you'll get
into into a gloomy mood Pink Floyd it's
all about yeah well all gloomy
topics one of their songs is called
brain damage one of their songs is
called Eclipse uh one of their albums is
called a momentary lapse of
Reason uh one of their songs is called
comfortably num and so on it's all
gloomy dark topics brain damage imagine
that the lunatics are on the
grass there's someone in my head but
it's not me the music is incredible but
overall it's not I mean it puts you in a
gloomy mood Leed zean is is all
about enjoy life there's also some
amount of angst in Leed Zeppelin's uh
lyrics and songs obviously when you have
the blues you're going to have some
angst but overall it's a much much more
happy band four very distinctive artists
musicians paig plant bonam and Jones so
overall I would say I would I would
prefer lead Zeppelin but if you were to
ask me which are the top two rock bands
Western rock bands in my opinion it's
number one Le zeppin number two ping
Floyd okay Nishant says Zaman is Persian
W is Arabic all right got it sir thank
you thank you so much appreciate
that okay
umil onel says tell me your most
favorite movies TV shows and tell me the
reason behind it look um you know what
they
say I have I mean I have seen so many
movies so many I'm a big movie fan by
the way movie buff these days I don't
watch too many movies because there are
no good movies anymore but if if I had
the choice I would watch movies in a on
the big screen every week as long as
they're showing good movies but these
days I hardly watch two movies a year on
the big screen because but I have seen
lots of movies lots and lots movies all
the classics I've seen Rashon I've seen
ran I've seen all the kurava movies I've
seen all the bud Spen teren Hill movies
which you may not even be aware of some
of the best entertainment of all time
especially if you're a kid Bud Spencer
Terren Hill I am for the hip-hop
tamas and uh Trinity my name is Trinity
and and so on so forth all the James
Bond movies of the 80s and 90s no longer
the 2000s yuck
yuck uh I was a big fan of Daniel Craig
but first movie Casino Royal was great
after that it's all gone downhill slowly
um what kind of movie genres do I like
science fiction I love science fiction
uh comedy I love comedy mask The Mask
it's a movie you can watch 100 times and
not get
bored um can't remember all my favorite
movies it's like you know I've had so
many meals in my life I can't remember
them all but they all made me who I am
similarly I've read uncountable books I
can't remember them all but they made me
who I am similarly I've watched so many
movies and TV shows I can't remember
them all but they kind of contributed to
who I am today in some way TV shows uh
Breaking Bad was good House of Cards was
good as long as that guy was there
Underwood Frank
Underwood uh what else what else Game of
Thrones was good for the first I don't
know Five Seasons or something they
ruined the last two
seasons and uh can't remember all them
all maybe I should make a separate video
on that my top 50 movies and top 50 Mo
TV shows or something like that science
fiction big fan I used to watch Star
Trek I used to I liked the first three
Star Wars movies The
Originals and so on so so much I can
speak about this for an hour but let me
stop
there
okay Ric power says how can I change the
world you change the world by
participating in
activities everything you
do has some effect on the
environment Quantum decoherence okay
I'll not go there so the thing is this
don't be an observer be a participant
that way you'll be able to change the
world in some way big or small not
everybody is meant to change the world
in a massive way but you can certainly
do something and and leave something
behind of yours right so the point is
don't merely observe what's happening
passively be an active
participant and the more a person of
substance you become over time the more
robust will be your participation and
the more impactful will be your
participation okay so that's what it is
invest in yourself develop yourself into
the best version of what you can be and
participate
wholeheartedly in whatever it is that
that interests you in whatever it is
that you believe in and try to make a
change that's how we change the world in
some way or the
other okay mlav again why doesn't the
Indian government reduce taxes on air
conditioners why don't they put aces in
public spaces public places I think they
should reduce taxes on air conditions
for sure I think uh the Indian summer is
very hot in some places in many parts of
India north south wherever so I think
air conditions should be air conditioner
should be declared a basic human right
in India and I think they should reduce
taxes drastically on air conditioners I
think that's that's a very good thought
you can't put air conditioners in public
SP places because of the way physics
works okay so for example it's like
trying to refrigerate a city you can't
refrigerate or air conditioner City
because you need a boundary between the
place between the the area or the amount
of air that you're Cooling and the
external air into which you need to
throw out the excess
heat but if you are trying
to essentially refrig air condition the
entire atmosphere that doesn't work
so air conditioning works in an enclosed
area
only okay that's that's the fundamental
principle so that's why you can't put
aces in public places I
mean unless you want to do it in a in a
in a mall or something yeah you can have
air conditioned mall I'm sure most malls
in India are air conditioned aren't they
even airports are air conditioned but
apart from that I mean if you want to
air air condition the Town Square that
won't happen
yeah right
okay okay what else what else what else
what
else uh let us see what else do we
have why doesn't India have any vasal
states like the US has and Russia has is
India too small to have vasal States
well some people would say that Bhutan
is a vasal state of
India but overall yeah India doesn't
have any vasal states like the Americans
have America the US has well the entire
EU is vasal and so on Russia it has a
Central Asian Nations that you could
consider to be in some ways to be its
wasal in some way and so on Belarus is
another example some would claim that
some would say that belus is is a India
is not that powerful
just as simple as that okay India is
still not powerful enough to have vasal
States um so for India to in the future
hypothetically have vasal States India
would need to be I would say at least
twice as powerful as as what it is today
in terms of hard power so it's a it's a
process it will take time and that's
simply why it is not the
case an Sharma says do you know music
theory in Metallica versus me Meade
music theory well yeah I have some
fundamental basic understanding of
scales and
notes and uh note progressions and the
the suage notation and whatnot because I
do play music occasionally not so much
anymore but I used to be kind of a
musician and I still can kind of play
the guitar so um and I have taken
interest I mean more than a passing
interest in in music I also play ragas
Indian ragas and so on so that's why I
do understand some music theory
Metallica versus Meade I am not a big
fan of trash metal or heavy metal
Metallica is not merely trash metal or
heavy metal they have uh a little more
quality so I would go with
Metalica Nishant says what are your
thoughts on the legends of vampire
vampires Dracula and demonic possession
I think like a I think that a disease
like RAB has played a huge role in the
formation of these myths I think the
legend of vampires was uh may have its
Origins either in the Black Death that
ravaged Europe in the Dark Ages Medieval
ages of
Europe or maybe in a disease that they
used to call
consumption which is actually
tuberculosis so when a person has
tuberculosis and if they're not treated
they start wasting away their skin
becomes pale they lose they they you
know the the redness goes away from
their cheeks they become entirely pale
and they cuff up blood and so on so that
is
very vampiric you know
traits and
uh so maybe the vampire mths had their
origins in consumption which is
tuberculosis and maybe the black death
um maybe ravies also because if somebody
has rabies human beings and they first
of all they become hydrophobic they
can't drink water they are unable ble to
swallow that they're fearful if you give
them a glass of water to to drink and uh
the traits behaviors that rabes patients
uh they they exhibit and so on
so so yeah maybe these are the origins
the actual factual origins of these
myths because we obviously know that
there are no vampires there's not
there's no demonic possession as far as
we know I hope there's not don't tell me
yeah there there you have it
um geopolitical du says I want to learn
Chinese please give me some suggestions
that's one language I have never
attempted to learn so I don't know what
to say uh what are the languages I have
tried learning well I
know well non-indian languages I only
know French and that's something I
didn't try learning I just learned
because I was a kid in a French speaking
country so I just picked up French in in
a couple of months kids learn very fast
they learn without even noticing that
they're learning uh what other language
have I tried learning I once learned the
Arabic script okay I had this gigantic
dictionary I had access to this gigantic
dictionary called the American Heritage
dictionary and if you go to the American
heritage heritage dictionary and you
open the uh you go to the uh entry for
alphabet then they have this entire list
of alphabets of many countries and one
of these was the Arabic alphabet alif
bet whatever it is yeah so one afternoon
I said let me learn this and in a couple
of hours I could write my name in Arabic
and I had learned enough that I could
write a lot in Arabic so um but that's
just the script not the language the
language is a very different language so
when it comes to learning a language you
have to spend several hours a day if you
want to learn fast you have to
essentially immerse yourself in that en
environment in which the language is all
you can speak in so there are some apps
that are available I don't know what
they're called one is Rosetta Stone I'm
not sure how good it is another app is
called dualingo and so on so uh I think
these apps are available many apps are
available these days some of them could
be really good that's what I could
suggest for you pick a good learning app
and spend a few hours per day at least a
couple of hours a day practicing
and and getting better
progressively but apart from that I
don't have any personal uh experience
with the Chinese language so I could not
go beyond giving you this General uh
philosophy of learning a new
language all right Bobby says don't you
watch English film I'm sorry Indian
films don't you watch Indian films there
certainly are some good ones here and
there the most Rec recent example is
12th fail I I haven't seen 12th fail I
have become so disillusioned with
Bollywood that I just don't watch in the
movies anymore which is the last movie I
saw I think it was bahubali b 2 but
that's not a Bollywood movie it's it's a
movie from the south I did watch rrr on
the small
screen because it was so much because
there was so much hype about it
especially in the west I was it was okay
not bad but there was a bit of
secularism in that as well yeah that is
something just just turns me off you
know this this forced
secularism what else I watched URI a few
years ago and uh what else can't
remember much more I'm sure there are
good movies here and there but because
of the overall lack of standards and and
low standards in Bollywood I just don't
feel like watching I mean there was a
time when I used to watch Bollywood
movies as a kid I watched many Bollywood
movies from the from those days uh
remember once I was in the US for a few
months and I watched we had DVDs those
days me and some of my colleagues and we
watched this movie D like I don't know
five six times wasn't a bad
movie that's like I don't know that
movie was what 20 years ago more than
more than 20 years ago there have been
good
movies but the number of bad the ratio
of bad movies to good movies is just way
too large today in Bollywood there's
nothing interesting from my perspective
you know and and when they make
historical movies they make something
like
moeno which I here was a ghastly movie
and then they make jod abbar which is
even
ghastlier and God knows what else I
would love to watch good movies really
but yeah I don't these
days what kind of PC or Ps games have
you played I had a PlayStation 2 all
these years ago um I played a car crash
game there was this game called I forget
the name of the game it was about car
racing you are in a race in a car and
you go around a racetrack you can choose
any RAC trck you want Silver Lake was
there and what other what other whatever
the places and it was more about
crashing cars unless you really spent
many hours of then you become really
good at that so there was that there was
something called Dynasty
Warriors and some other games that was
the PlayStation 2 that I had today you
have PlayStation 4 I think or five I
don't know which one it is today and PC
games I have played Tetris I have played
something called snood I played mind
sweeper and that's about it I'm not a
big gaming guy that's about
it do I like Tarantino movies Pulp
Fiction is great Pulp Fiction is one of
the great movies Tarantino is overall
great stylistically great story is great
some of the movies are a little
self-indulgent but over overall his
movies are
great uh pul fiction obviously one of
his great movies what else uh why do I
forget the names of
movies pul fiction great um what's that
movie from morning from night to day or
something a movie that looks like a
western but it becomes a vampire movie
that was kind of weird but kind of
good uh yeah i' I've seen most Tarantino
movies and I am big big fan of quentine
Tarantino uh there was something called
four four rooms four
rooms that was a good movie and and many
more
sorry
okay tarun says do you believe in the
ramayan I believe it is a it is it was a
historical event I believe it was
but we our archaeologists have not done
enough to
investigate the
historicity so we are still at the point
they ensure that they will not go and do
their job and that's why we don't have
any hard evidence of when it happened
and where it happened I mean go and
investigate the ramu go and investigate
obviously aodha is all
destroyed the the ancient city of aodha
which existed a thousand 1,000 years ago
has been totally destroyed by the Turks
so a lot of the evidence has been
destroyed and all but overall to answer
a question I am convinced these are all
historical events which happened a long
long long time ago maybe several
thousand years ago for
sure sidhar says what should be our road
to becoming a superpower okay so you
want to you want to fly before you fly
you have to run very fast Sprint but
before you sprint you have to be able to
run at a medium pace and before you to
know how to run at a medium pace you
need to know how to jog run slowly and
before you know how to jog you have to
know how to
walk so superpow is flying but we are
the we are now beginning to jog for the
first time ever in the in the past
thousand years so let's take it step by
step superp power is 70 years from now
50 years from now I don't know why
Indians are obsessed with this
superpower status it's about status no
right now India should be a great power
in the Indian Ocean region in the next
10 to 15 years that is far from being a
superpower but for now that will be do
and then work on on the economy and
eventually you may reach the super power
status by 2050 2060 or so it's not
something that will happen next year or
next week or whatever it's a long
process but we are on track towards
becoming a genuine great power there are
lots of hurdles in the way but it takes
time so let's not talk about being a
superpower that's only one superpower
you know why they are a superpower the
United States they have more than 800
extra territorial military bases outside
of their territory that's why they are a
superpower and also because they control
the world's Reserve currency the US
dollar okay so that is something that
you can Aspire for in 50 years perhaps
so let's be realistic and do and take it
one step at a time when you want to
climb Mount Everest you don't look at
the top you look at the next 100 MERS
and you ensure that you do it step by
step and do those 100 meters really well
once you do that you look at the next
100 meters and you do that over and over
and over and over again and if you keep
on doing it properly you're going to
reach there but it'll take time so there
you have it okay let's take one or two
more questions and then we will be
done update on the KV offense offensive
by Russia it's something that's ongoing
the situation is very fluid right now so
let's not comment about it maybe in a
week's time when some when we have
proper data and information on what's
Happening then maybe I'll speak about
this when something is happening in real
time there's no point really commenting
okay the Russians have initiated an
offensive they may want to take karv the
city you want to see where it is I can
do that okay let's find out where karv
is okay Ukraine and karv is over here
you see here so they had almost taken
the city two years ago the Russians but
then they went when they they let it go
so now they may be on the verge or they
may be positioning themselves to take
this city and as you can see it's not
really far from the Russian border so
it's not really e really that hard for
them to take it if they want to
so there's an offens going on right now
and it's too early to comment about it
because it's a work in progress It's a
fluid situation maybe in a week's time I
could take this question up and we will
see okay red
says who are the Wun people I I don't
know I'm sorry I look it up but right
now I don't have an answer because I'm
not aware of it
sorry okay
it's a mystery where he's taking these
questions from don't Twitter hasht
questions count okay I am looking at the
at the at the uh YouTube live chat
that's what I'm looking at uh I'm not
looking at Twitter right now because I
only have one screen in front of me I
canot look at seven different screens I
have one screen here I have one screen
here for the map over here which you
can't see but I'm putting the map on the
screen I cannot take questions from two
or three different sources so I'm not
doing it from from Twitter right now you
can view this on Twitter but I'm not
taking questions from Twitter it's only
from the YouTube live chat and if you
look at the title of this live stream it
says asking anything live chat
so
yeah okay speak about politics in Goa I
have absolutely no idea about politics
in Goa very sorry I don't look at
India's internal
politics Mani asks a good question are
you doing research in your field
currently currently I'm not doing
research in physics currently and that
is something I'm very dis dissatisfied
about so uh it's something I do need to
get back into active research in physics
but right now I'm not doing that and
thanks for the reminder appreciate
that okay
um pru says uh open AI launched chat gb2
40 and I think we cooked what's your
reaction on this development look new
and more powerful language learning
models are going to be released every
few months not just by open a but from
the others as well everybody is going to
have one so yeah that's where we are
it's it's going to the the
pace of these technological improvements
is going to keep on increasing and maybe
at some point in time we will have AGI
artificial general intelligence and then
we cooked it is the singularity it is
what Skynet the Skynet moment we'll see
let's see nothing we can do about it
where we
are uh last question for today adiya
says your views on India dominating
chess yeah brilliant I'm I'm I'm loving
it we have Vali
the the latest run Master her brother
prananda is doing very well gukesh
recently won the candidates
championships the two can candidates
tournament is going to challenge ding
Len the current champion at the end of
this year lots of young young really
young Indians are coming and and
dominating the field prananda has beaten
Magnus Carlson the world number one
multiple times at least twice that I can
think of it's great to see wonderful and
the old Grand Master vishwanath is still
around so it is great to say this and
we're going to see more of this we're
going to see a
whole tsunami of Indians dominating not
just chess but all sports in this coming
decade India is going to be a sports
superpower in this coming decade watch
out for it all right uh that's it for
today we have crossed 2 hours 13 minutes
so that is it I will see you in the next
live stream which is going to be most
likely this Friday if I'm not mistaken
until then thank you very much for
watching I appreciate your viewership
and I will see you very soon in the next
live stream until then take care bye-bye
and don't forget to keep raising your
standards